<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two dyaloges wrytten in laten by the famous clerke, D.Erasm[us] of Roterodame, one called Polyphemus or the gospeller, the other dysposyng of thynges and names, translated in to Englyshe by Edmonde Becke. And prynted at Cantorbury in saynt Paules paryshe by Ioh[a]n Mychell</title>
            <title>Colloquia. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111335</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846700</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846700</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11687</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00336)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11687)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 38:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two dyaloges wrytten in laten by the famous clerke, D.Erasm[us] of Roterodame, one called Polyphemus or the gospeller, the other dysposyng of thynges and names, translated in to Englyshe by Edmonde Becke. And prynted at Cantorbury in saynt Paules paryshe by Ioh[a]n Mychell</title>
                  <title>Colloquia. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.</author>
                  <author>Becke, Edmund, 16th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In saynt Paules paryshe by Ioh[a]n Mychell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Prynted at Cantorbury :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1550?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dialogues, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11687:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11687:1"/>
            <p>¶ Two dyaloges wrytten in laten by the famous clerke D. Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mꝰ of Roterodame / one called Polyphemus or the goſpeller / the other dyſpoſyng of thynges and names / tranſlated in to Englyſh by Edmonde Becke.</p>
            <p>And prynted at Cantorbury in ſaynt Paules paryſhe by Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mychell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:11687:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11687:2"/>
            <head>The preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Vcius Anneus Seneca amonge many other pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſaienges (gentle reder) hathe this alſo, whiche in my iudgement is as trew as it is wittie. Roga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do cogit qui rogat ſuperior. And in effecte is thus moch to ſay, yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſuperior or his better de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyre any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, he might aſwell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de it by authoritie as ones to deſyre it.</p>
            <p>A gentleman a nere coſyn of myne, but moch nerer in fryndſhyp, efteſones dyd inſtant and moue me to tranſlate theſe two dyaloges folowynge, to whoſe ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tlenes I am ſo moch obliged, indetted and bounde, that he myght well haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded me to this and more pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: to whome I do not onely owe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce, but my ſelfe alſo. And in acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhynge of his moſt honeſt requeſt (part<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly bycauſe I wolde not the mooſt inhu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mane fawte of Ingratitude ſhuld wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thely
<pb facs="tcp:11687:3"/> be imputed to me, &amp; that I might in this thynge alſo (accordynge to my bounden dutie) gratifie my frende) I haue haſſard my ſelfe in theſe daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous dayes, where many are ſo capcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſome prone and redy to malygne &amp; depraue, and fewe whoſe eares are not ſo feſtidious, tendre, and redy to pleaſe, that in very tryfles &amp; thynges of ſmall importaunce, yet exacte dylygence and exquiſite iudgement is loked for and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quyred, of them whiche at this preſent wyll attempte to tranſlate any boke be it that the matter be neuer ſo baſe. But what diligence I haue enployed in the tranſlacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereof I referre it to the iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement of the lerned ſort, whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge my tranſlacion with the laten dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aloges, I dowte not wyl condone and pardone my boldneſſe, in that that I chalenge the ſemblable lybertie whiche the tranſlatours of this tyme iuſtlie chalenge. For ſome here tofore ſubmyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng them ſelfe to ſeruytude, haue lytle
<pb facs="tcp:11687:3"/> reſpecte to the obſeruacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the thyng which in tranſlacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is of all other moſt neceſſary and requiſite, that is to ſaye, to rendre the ſence &amp; the very meanyng of the author, not ſo relygyouſlie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicte to tranſlate worde for worde, for ſo the ſence of the author is oftentimes corrupted &amp; depraued, and neyther the grace of the one tonge nor yet of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is truely obſerued or aptlie expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. The lerned knoweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery tonge hathe his peculyer proprietie, phraſe, maner of locucion, enargies and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, which ſo aptlie in any other to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g can not be expreſſed. Yf I ſhal perceyue this my ſymple doinge to be thankeful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly taken, and in good parte accepted, it ſhall encorage me hereafter to attempte the tranſlacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſome bokes dyſpoſing of matters bothe delectable, frutefull, &amp; expedient to be knowen, by the grace of God, who gyuynge me quyetnes of mynde, lybertie, and abylytie, ſhall not deſyſte to communicat the frute of my
<pb facs="tcp:11687:4"/> ſpare howers, to ſuch as are not lerned in the laten tonge: to whome I dedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat the fyrſte frutes of this my ſymple tranſlacyon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="definition">
            <head>A declaracion of the names.</head>
            <p>POliphemus ſygnifieth, valyant or noble, and in an other ſygnifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacion, talcatyfe or clybbe of tong. The name of a Gyant called Cyclops, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge but one eye in his forhed, of a huge ſtature and a myghtie ꝑſonage. And is aplyed here to ſygnifie a great freke or a lubber, as this Poliphemus was, whiche beynge a man of warre or a courtyer, had a newe teſtament in his hande, and loked buſelie for ſome ſentence or text of ſcrypture and that Cannius his companyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſpyed and ſayd to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:11687:4"/>
            <head>¶ The parſons names are Cannius and Poliphemus.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Annius.</speaker>
               <p>what hunt Poliphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me for here?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>Aſke ye what I hunt for here, and yet ye ſe me haue neyther dogges, dart, Iauelyn, nor huntyng ſtaffe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>Paraduenture ye hunt after ſome pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nymphe of the couert.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemus.</speaker>
               <p>By my trouth and well coniectured, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holde what a goodly purſenet, or a hay I haue here in my hande.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicite, what a ſtraunge ſyght is this, me thinke I ſe Bachus in a lyons ſkin, Poliphemus with a boke in his hande. This is a dogge in a doblet, a ſowe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſadle, of all that euer I ſe it is a non decet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>I haue not onely payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and garnyſſhed my boke with ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, but alſo I haue lymmed it withe Sinople, aſapherida, redleed, vermilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and byſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>It is a warlyke boke, for it is furniſſhed with knottes, taſſils
<pb facs="tcp:11687:5"/> plates, claſpes, and braſen bullyons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>Take the boke in your hand and loke within it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>I ſe it wery well. Truly it is a praty boke, but me thynkes ye haue not yet trymmed it ſufficiently for all your coſt ye haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>why what lac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſhuldeſt haue ſet thyne armes vpon it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>what armes I beſeche the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>Mary the heed of Silenus, an olde iolthed drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard totynge out of a hoggeſhed or a tunne, but in good erneſt, wherof dothe your boke dyſpoſe or intreate? dothe it teache the art and crafte to drynke a duetaunt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Take hede in goddes name what ye ſay leſt ye bolt out a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemie before ye be ware.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>why bydde ye me take hede what I ſaye? is there any holy matt in the boke?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is the goſpell boke, I trow there is nothynge can be more holye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>God for thy grace what hathe Poliphemus to do withe the goſpell?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:11687:5"/>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Nay why do ye not aſke what a chryſten man hathe to do with chriſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>I can not tell but me thynkes a rouſty byll or a halbard wold become ſuch a great lubber or a ſlouyn as thou arte a great deale better, for yf it were my chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to mete ſuch one and knewe him not vpon ſeeborde, and he loked ſo lyke a knaue and a ruffya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thou doſt I wolde take hym for a pirate or a ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vpon the ſee / and if I met ſuch one in the wood for an arrante thefe, and a man murderer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>yea good ſyr but the goſpell teache vs this ſame leſſon, that we ſhuld not iudge any perſon by his loke or by his externall &amp; outwarde apparaunce. For lyke wyſe as many tymes vnder a graye freers coote a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous mynde lyeth ſecretly hyd, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo apolled heed, a criſpe or a twyrled berde, a frowninge, a ferſe, or a dogged loke, a cappe, or a hat with an oyſtrich fether, a ſoldyers caſſocke, a payre of hoofe all to cut and manglyd, may co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:11687:6"/> an euangelycall mynde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>why not, mary God forbyd elles, yea &amp; many tymes a ſymple ſhepe lyeth hyd in a wolfes ſkynne, and yf a man maye credite and beleue the fables of Aeſope, an aſſe maye lye ſecretely vnknowen by cauſe he is in a lyons ſkynne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>Naye I knowe hym whiche bereth a ſhepe vpon his heed, and a foxe in his breſt, to whome I wold wyſſhe with al my hart that he had as whyte and as fauorable frendes as he hathe blacke eyes. And I wolde wyſſhe alſo that he were aſwell guylt ouer and ouer as he hathe a colour mete to take guyltynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>Yf ye take hym to were a ſhepe vpon his heed, that weareth a cappe of woll, howe greuouſly than art thou lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyn, or what an excedynge heuy burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beareſt thou then I praye the whiche beareſt a hoole ſhepe and an oſtryche to vpon thy heed? But what ſaye ye to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth not he more folyſſly which beareth a byrd vpon his heed, and an aſſe in his
<pb facs="tcp:11687:6"/> breſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemus.</speaker>
               <p>There ye nypped &amp; taunted me in dede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>But I wolde ſaye this geere dyd wonderous wel yf this goſpel boke dyd ſo adourne the with vertue as thou haſt adourned lymmed, and gorgiouſly garnyſſhed it with many gay goodly glyſtryng orna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes. Mary ſyr thou haſt ſet it forth in his ryght colours in dede, wolde to god it might ſo adourne the with good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that thou myghteſt ones lerne to be an honeſt man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>There ſhall be no defaute in me, I tell you I wyll do my diligence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>Naye there is no doute of that, there ſhall be no more faute in you now I dare ſay then was wonte to be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but (youre tarte tauntes, and youre churlyſſhe checkes, and raylynges ſet aſyde) tell me I pray the this one thynge, do you thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayſe, condempne, or fynde faute with them whiche caryeth aboute with them the newe teſtament or the goſpel boke?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>No by my fayth do I not good
<pb facs="tcp:11687:7"/> praty man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>Call ye me but a praty one and I am hygher then you by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> length of a good aſſes heed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>I thynke not fully ſo moche yf the aſſe ſtretch forth his eares, but go to it ſkyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lis no matter of that, let it paſſe, he that bare Chriſt vpon his backe was called Chriſtofer, and thou whiche beareſt the goſpell boke aboute with the ſhall for Poliphemus be called the goſpeller or the goſpell bearer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Polip.</speaker>
               <p>Do not you counte it an holy thynge to cary aboute with a man the newe teſtament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ni.</speaker>
               <p>why no ſyr by my trouth do I not, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou graunte the very aſſes to be holy to.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>How can an aſſe be holy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>For one aſſe alone is able to beare thre hundreth ſuche bokes, and I thynke ſuche a great lubber as thou art were ſtronge inoughe to beare as great a burden, and yf thou had a han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome packeſadle ſette vpon thy backe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>And yet for all your ieſtynge it is not agaynſt good reaſon to ſaye
<pb facs="tcp:11687:7"/> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſe was holy whiche bore chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>I do not enuye you man for this holynes for I had as lefe you had that holynes as I, and yf it pleaſe you to take it I wyll geue you an holy &amp; a religious relyke of the ſelfe ſame aſſe whiche chriſt rode vpon, and whan ye haue it ye may kyſſe it lycke it and cull it as ofte as ye lyſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Mary ſyr I thanke you, ye can not gyue me a more thanckefull gyfte nor do me a greatter pleaſure, for that aſſe withouten any fayle was made as holye as any aſſe could be by the touchynge of chriſtes body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>Vndouted they touched chriſtes body alſo whiche ſtroke and buffeted chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>yea but tell me this one thynge I praye the in good erneſt. Is it not a great ſygne of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in a man to cary aboute the goſpel boke or the newe teſtament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>It is a token of holynes in dede if it be done without hypocryſie, I meane if it be done without diſſimulacion / and for
<pb facs="tcp:11687:8"/> that end, intent &amp; purpoſe, that it ſhuld be done for.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>What the deuyl &amp; a morten telleſt thou a man of warre of hypocriſie, away with hypocriſie to the monkes and the freers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but bycauſe ye ſaye ſo, tell me fyrſte I praye you what ye call hypocriſie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>When a man pretendis another thyng outwardly then he meanis ſecretly in his mynde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>But what dothe the bearynge aboute of the newe teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſygnyfie. Dothe it not betoken that thy lyfe ſhulde be conformable to the goſpell which thou carryeſt aboute with the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>I thynke well it dothe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>Wel then when thy lyfe is not conformable to the boke, is not that playne hypocriſie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliph.</speaker>
               <p>Tell me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what you call the trewe carienge of the goſpell boke aboute with a man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ni.</speaker>
               <p>So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me men beare it aboute with them in theyr ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des (as the gray freers were wonte to beare the rule of ſaynt Fraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces) and ſo the porters of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Aſſes
<pb facs="tcp:11687:8"/> &amp; horſes may beare it as well as they. And there be ſome other that carry the goſpel in theyr mouthes onlie, and ſuch haue no other talke but al of chriſt and his goſpell, and that is a very poynt of a pharyſey. And ſome other carrye it in theyr myndes. But in myne opynion he beares the goſpell boke as he ſhuld do whiche bothe beares it in his hande, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munes of it with his mouth whan occa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon of edyfyenge of his neyghboure whan conuenyent oportunytie is my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſtred to him, and alſo beares it in his mynde and thynkes vpon it withe his harte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Yea thou art a mery felow, where ſhall a man fynde ſuche blacke ſwa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>In euery cathedrall church, where there be any deacons, for they beare the goſpel boke i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, they ſynge the goſpell aloude, ſomtyme in a lofte that the people may heare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, althoughe they do not vnderſtand it, and theyr myndes are vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it when they ſynge it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Polphe.</speaker>
               <p>And yet for all your
<pb facs="tcp:11687:9"/> ſayenge all ſuche deacons are no ſaync<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that beare the goſpell ſo in theyr myndes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>But leſt ye play the ſubtyle and capcious ſophyſtryar with me I wyll tell you this one thynge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. No man can beare the goſpell in his mynde but he muſt nedes loue it from the bothum of his harte, no man loueth it inwardly and from the bothu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his harte but he muſt nedes declare and expreſſe the goſpell in his lyuinge, outwarde maners, &amp; behauour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>I can not ſkyll of youre ſubtyle reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges, ye are to fyne for me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wyll commune with you after a groſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſer maner, and more playnly. yf thou dyddeſt beare a tankard of good Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe wyne vpon thy ſhulders onelye, what other thynge were it to the then a burden.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>It were none other thynge truly, it is no great pleaſure to beare wyne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>What and yf thou dranke aſmoche as thou coudeſt well holde in thy mouthe, after the maner of
<pb facs="tcp:11687:9"/> a gargariſme &amp; ſpyt it out agayne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>That wolde do me no good at all, but take me not with ſuche a faute I trow, for the wyne is very bad and if I do ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>But what and yf thou drynke thy ſkynne full as thou art wont to do, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou comeſt where good wyne is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>Mary there is nothyng more godly or heuynly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>It warmes you at the ſtomacke, it ſettes your body in a heate, it makes you loke with a ruddy face, and ſetteth your hart vpon a mery pynne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>That is ſuerly ſo as ye ſaye in dede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>The goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is ſuche a lyke thynge of all this worlde, for after that it hathe ones per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; entered in the veynes of the mynd it altereth, tranſpoſeth, and cleane chan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth vpſodowne the whole ſtate of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and chaungeth hym cleane as it were into a nother man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Polip.</speaker>
               <p>Ah ha, nowe I wot wherabout ye be, belyke ye thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke that I lyue not accordynge to the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell or as a good goſpeller ſhulde do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:11687:10"/>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>There is no man can dyſſolue this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better then thy ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Call ye it diſſoluynge? Naye and yf a thynge come to dyſſoluynge gyue me a good ſharpe axe in my hande and I trow I ſhall dyſſolue it well inoughe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>What woldeſt thou do, I praye the, and yf a man ſhulde ſay to thy teth thou lyeſt falſely, or elles call the by thy ryght name knaue in englyſſhe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>What wolde I do quod he, that is a queſtion in dede, mary he ſhulde feele the wayghte of a payre of churlyſhe fyſtes I warrant the.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>And what and yf a man gaue you a good cuffe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the eare that ſhulde waye a pounde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>It were a well geuen blowe that wolde aduauntage hym .xx. by my trouthe and he eſcaped ſo he myght ſay he roſe vpon his ryght ſyde, but it were maruayle &amp; I cut not of his head harde by his ſhulders.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but good folowe thy goſpell boke teacheth the to geue gentle anſwers, and fayre wordes
<pb facs="tcp:11687:10"/> agayne for fowle, and to hym that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the a blowe vpon the ryght cheke to holde forth the lyfte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>I do remembre I haue red ſuche a thinge in my boke, but ye muſt pardone me for I had quyte forgotten it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>Well go to, what ſaye ye to prayer I ſuppoſe ye praye very ofte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>That is euyn as very a touche of a phareſey as any can be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>I graunt it is no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a poynte of a phareſey to praye longe and faynedly vnder a colour or prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of holynes, that is to ſaye when a man prayeth not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bothum of his hart but with the lyppes only and from the tethe outward, and that in opyn places where great reſort of people is, bycauſe they wold be ſene. But thy goſpel boke teacheth the to praye contynually, but ſo that thy prayer come from the bothu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the hart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but yet for all my ſayenge I praye ſumtyme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>When I beſeche the when y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art a ſlepe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>When it cometh in to my mynde, ones
<pb facs="tcp:11687:11"/> or twyſe may chaunce in a weke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>what prayer ſayſt thou?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>The lordes prayer, the Pater noſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>Howe many tymes ouer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Onis, &amp; I trowe it is often inoughe, for the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell forbyddeth often repetynge of one thynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>Can ye ſaye your pater noſter through to an ende &amp; haue youre mynde runnynge vpon nothynge elles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all that whyle?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>By my trouthe and ye wyll beleue me I neuer yet aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed nor proued whether I coulde do it or no. But is it not ſufficient to ſaye it with my mouthe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>I can not tell whether it be or no. But I am ſure god here vs not excepte we praye from the bothum of our harte. But tell me ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thyng I wyll aſke the. Doeſt thou not faſt very often?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>No neuer in all my lyfe tyme and yf it were not for lacke of meate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>And yet thy boke alowes and commendes hyghly bothe faſtynge and prayer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Polip.</speaker>
               <p>So coulde I alowe them to but that my belly can
<pb facs="tcp:11687:11"/> not well affare nor away with faſtyng.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but Paule ſayth they are not the ſeruauntes of Ieſus Chriſte whiche ſerue theyr belly &amp; make it theyr god. Do you eate fleſhe euery day?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Po.</speaker>
               <p>No neuer when I haue none to eate, but I neuer refuſe it when it is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, and I neuer aſke queſtion not for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience but for my belly ſake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but theſe ſtronge ſturdy ſydes of ſuche a chuffe and a lobbynge lobye as thou arte wolde be fed well inoughe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haye and barke of trees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but chryſte ſayd, that which entereth in at the mouthe defyleth not the man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>That is to be vnderſtand thus yf it be meaſurably taken, and without the offendinge of our chriſtian brother. But Paule the diſciple of chryſt had ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther peryſhe &amp; ſterue with hunger then onys to offende his weyke brothren w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his catynge, and he exhorteth vs to fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe his example that in all thynges we maye pleaſe all men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli,</speaker>
               <p>What tel
<pb facs="tcp:11687:12"/> ye me of Paule, Paule is Paule and I am I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>Do you gladly helpe to releue the poore and the indygent with your goodes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>Howe can I helpe them whiche haue nothynge to gyue them, and ſcant inoughe for my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>ye myght ſpare ſomthynge to helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with yf thou woldeſt playe the good huſband in lyuynge more wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, in moderatynge thy ſuperfluous expenſes, and in fallynge to thy worke luſtely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>Nay then I were a fole in dede, a peny worth of eaſe is euer worth a peny, and nowe I haue found ſo moch pleaſure in eaſe that I can not fall to no labour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>Do you kepe the commaundementes of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Polip.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe ye appoſe me, kepe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes ꝙ he, that is a payne in dede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>Art thou ſory for thy ſynnes and thyne offences, doeſt thou erneſtly repent the for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemus.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt hath payed the raunſome of ſynne and ſatiſfied for it alredy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>Howe
<pb facs="tcp:11687:12"/> proueſt thou then that thou loueſt the goſpell and fauoris the word of god as thou beareſt men in hande thou doeſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemus.</speaker>
               <p>I wyll tell you that by &amp; by, and I dare ſaye you wyl confeſſe no leſſe your ſelfe then that I am an erneſt fauorer of the worde when I haue told you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tale. There was a certayne gray frere of the order of ſaynt Fraunces w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs whiche neuer ceaſed to bable and rayle agaynſte the newe teſtament of Eraſmus, I chaunſed to talke with the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tylman pryuatly where no man was preſent but he and I, and after I had communed awhyle with hym I caught my frere by the polled pate with my left hande and with my right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de I drew out my daggar and I pomelled the knaue frere welfauardly aboute his ſkonce that I made his face as ſwollen and as puffed as a puddynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>what a tale is this that thou telleſt me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemus.</speaker>
               <p>How ſay you is not this a good and a ſufficient proue that I fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:11687:13"/> the goſpell. I gaue hym abſolucion afore he departed out of my handes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this newe teſtament thryſe layde vpon his pate as harde as I myght dryue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I made thre bunches in his heed as bygge as thre egges in the name of the father, the ſone, &amp; the holy gooſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Can.</speaker>
               <p>Now by my trouth this was well done &amp; lyke a ryght goſpeller of theſe dayes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ly this is as they ſaye to dyffende the goſpell with the goſpell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t another graye frere of the ſame curry ſhe couent, that knaue neuer had done in raylynge agaynſt Eraſmus, ſo ſone as I had eſpyed hym I was ſtyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and moued with the brenninge zele of the goſpell that in thretenyng of him I made hym knele downe vpon his knees and crye Eraſmus mercie and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſired me to forgyue him, I may ſaye to you it was hyghe tyme for hym to fall downe vpon his marybones, and yf he had not done it by and by I had my hal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>barde
<pb facs="tcp:11687:13"/> vp redy to haue gyuen hym be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twyxt the necke and the heade, I loked as grymme as modie Mars when he is in furyous fume, it is trewe that I tell you, for there was inoughe ſawe the frere and me yf I wolde make a lye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>I maruayle the frere was not out of his wyt. But to retourne to oure purpoſe agayne, doſt thou lyue chaſtly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemus.</speaker>
               <p>Peraduenture I maye do here after when I am more ſtryken in age. But ſhall I confeſſe the trouthe to the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>I am no preeſt man, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore yf thou wylt be ſhryuen thou muſt ſeke a preeſt to whome thou maye be lawfully confeſſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>I am wont ſtyl to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe my ſelfe to god, but I wyl confeſſe thus moche to the at this tyme I am not yet become a perfyte goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler or an euangelical man, for I am but yet as it were one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune people, ye knowe wel perde we goſpellers haue iiii. goſpels wrytten by the .iiii. euange<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyſtes,
<pb facs="tcp:11687:14"/> &amp; ſuche goſpellers as I am hunt buſely, and chefely for .iiii. thynges that we may haue. Vnde. to prouyde dayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fare for the bellie, that nothynge be lackynge to that parte of the body whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che nature hath placed vnder the belly, ye wote what I meane, and to obtayne and procure ſuche liuinge that we may lyue welthely and at pleaſure without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arke &amp; care. And fynally that we maye do what we lyſt without checke or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolment, yf we goſpellars lacke none of all theſe thynges we crye and ſynge for ioye, amonge our ful cuppes Io Io we tryumphe and are wonderfull fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycke, we ſynge and make as mery as cup and can, and ſaye the goſpell is a lyue agayne Chryſt rayneth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>This is a lyfe for an Epycure or a god belly and for no euangelicall perſone that profeſſeth the goſpell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye not but that it is ſo as ye ſaye, but ye knowe well that god is omnipotent and can do al thynges, he can turne vs
<pb facs="tcp:11687:14"/> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his wyll is ſodenly in to other ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>So can he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme you in to hogges and ſwyne, the whiche maye ſoner be done I iudge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to chaunge you in to good men for ye are halfe ſwynyſhe &amp; hoggyſhe alredy, your lyuynge is ſo beaſtlie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>Holde thy peas ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wolde to god there were no men that dyd more hurt in the world then ſwyne, bullockes, aſſes, and camelles. A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſe many men now adayes more crueller then lyons, more rauenynge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wolues, more lecherous then ſparous, and that byte worſe then mad dogges, more noyſom the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſnakes, vepers and adders.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>But nowe good Polipheme remembre and loke vpon thy ſelfe for it is hyghe tyme for the to laye a ſyde thy beaſtly lyuynge, and to be tourned from a brute and a ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uage beaſt in to a man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke you good neyghbour Cannius for by ſaynt Mary I thynke your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle is good / for the prophetes of this
<pb facs="tcp:11687:15"/> tyme ſayth the worlde is almoſt at an end, and we ſhall haue domes daye (as they call it) ſhortely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canniꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>We haue therfore more nede to <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>pare our ſelues in a redines agaynſt that day, and that with as moche ſpede as maye be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemus.</speaker>
               <p>as for my part I loke and wayte ſtyll euery day for the mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty hande and power of chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>Take hede therfore that thou, when chriſt ſhall laye his myghty hande vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the be as tendre as waxe, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to his eternall wyll he maye fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp; faſhyon the with his hande. But wherby I praye the dothe theſe prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes coniecture &amp; gather that the worlde is almoſt at an ende.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>Bycauſe men
<stage>(they ſaye)</stage> do the ſelfe ſame thinge nowe adayes that they dyd, and were wont to do which were lyuynge in the worlde a lytle whyle before the deluge or Noyes floode. They make ſolempne feaſtes, they banket, they quaffe, they booll, they bybbe, they ryot men mary,
<pb facs="tcp:11687:15"/> wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are maryed, they go a catterwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge and horehuntinge, they bye, they ſell, they lend to vſerie, and borowe vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on vſerie, they builde, ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges kepe warre one agaynſt another, preeſtes ſtudie howe they maye get many benefyces and promocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to make them ſelfe riche and increaſe theyr worldly ſubſtaunce, the diuynes make inſolible ſillogiſmus and vnperfyte argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, they gather concluſyons, monkes and freers ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, at rouers ouer all the world, the comyn people are in a maſe or a hurle burle re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy to make inſurrections, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude breuelie there lackes no euyll mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie nor myſchefe, neyther ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, thyrſt fellonie, robberie, warre, peſtilence, ſedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, derth, and great ſcarſytie and lacke of all good thynges. And howe ſay you do not all theſe thynges argue and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficientlie proue that the worlde is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at an ende?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but tell me I praye the of all thes hoole hepe of euyls and miſeries whiche greueth the
<pb facs="tcp:11687:16"/> moſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphemus.</speaker>
               <p>Whiche thynkes thou, tell me thy fanſie and coniecture?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>That the Deuyll (god ſaue vs) maye daunce in thy purſe for euer a croſſe that thou haſt to kepe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forthe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>I pray god I dye and yf thou haue not hyt the nayle vpon the head. Now as chaunceth I come newly from a knotte of good companye where we haue dronke harde euery man for his parte, &amp; I am not behynde with myne, and therfore my wytte is not halfe ſo freſhe as it wyll be, I wyll dyſpute of the goſpell with the whan I am ſobre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Canni.</speaker>
               <p>When ſhal I ſe the ſobre?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poli.</speaker>
               <p>When I ſhall be ſobre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll that be?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliph.</speaker>
               <p>When thou ſhalt ſeme, in the meane ſeaſon god be with you gentle Cannius and well mot you do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cannius.</speaker>
               <p>And I wyſhe to you a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne for my parte that thou ware in dede as valiaunt or puſaunt a felowe as thy name ſoundeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poliphe.</speaker>
               <p>And bycauſe ye ſhall loſe nothynge at my
<pb facs="tcp:11687:16"/> hande with wyſhynge I pray god that Cannius maye neuer lacke a good can or a ſtoope of wyne or bere, wherof he had his name.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="definition">
            <head>¶ The dialoge of thynges and names. A declaracion of the names.</head>
            <p>BEatus, is he whiche hathe abun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dance of al thinges that is good, and is parfyte in all thynges commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable or prayſe worthy or to be deſyred of a good man. Somtyme it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for fortunate, ryche, or noble. Bonifaciꝰ, fayre, full of fauor or well fauored.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:11687:17"/>
            <head>¶ The parſons names are Beatus and Bonifacius.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eatus.</speaker>
               <p>God ſaue you may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter Boniface.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bonifaciꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>God ſaue you &amp; god ſaue you agayne ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle Beatus. But I wold god bothe we were ſuch, and ſo in very dede as we be called by name, that is to ſay thou riche &amp; I fayre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beatus.</speaker>
               <p>Why do you thynke it nothynge worth at al to haue a good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly glorious name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bonifacius.</speaker>
               <p>Truely me thynke it is of no valure or lytle good worthe, onles a man haue the thynge it ſelfe whiche is ſygnified by the name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beatus.</speaker>
               <p>Yea you maye well thynke your pleaſure, but I am aſſured that the moſt part of all mortall men be of another mynde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bonifa.</speaker>
               <p>It may wel be I do not denye that they are mortal, but ſuerly I do not byleue that they are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which are ſo beaſtly mynded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Yes good ſyr and they be men to laye
<pb facs="tcp:11687:17"/> your lyfe, onleſſe ye thynke camels and aſſes do walke aboute vnder the fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure and forme of men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Mary I can ſoner beleue that then that they be men whiche eſteme and paſſe more vpon the name, then the thynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>I graunte in certayne kyndes of thinges mooſt men had rather haue the thynge then the name, but in many thynges it is otherwyſe and cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>I can not well tell what ye meane by that</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>And yet the example of this matter is apparant or ſufficiently declared in vs two. Thou arte called Bonifacius and thou haſt in dede the thynge wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou beareſt thy name. yet if there were no other remedy but eyther thou muſt lacke the one or the other, whether had you rather haue a fowle and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med face or elles for Boniface be called Maleface or horner?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Beleue me I had rather be called fowle Therſites then haue a monſtrous or a deformyd face, whether I haue a good face or no
<pb facs="tcp:11687:18"/> I can not tell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>And euen ſo had I for yf I were ryche and there were no re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>medy but that I muſt eyther forgoo my rycheſſe, or my name I had rather be cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Irus whiche was a poore beggers name then lacke my ryches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to you for aſmoch as ye ſpeake the trouth, and as you thynke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Iudge all them to be of the ſame mynde that I am of whiche are indued with helthe or other commodities and qualities ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>partaynynge to the body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>That is very trewe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Yea but I praye the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder and marke howe many men we ſe whiche had rather haue the name of a lerned and a holy man, then to be well lerned, vertuous, &amp; holy in dede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>I knowe a good ſorte of ſuche men for my part.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Tell me thy fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſie I pray the do not ſuche men paſſe more vpon the name then the thinge?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Methynke thy do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Yf we had a logician here whiche could well and clarkelie defyne what were a kynge, what a byſſhoppe,
<pb facs="tcp:11687:18"/> what a magiſtrate, what a philoſopher is, ꝑadue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture we ſhuld find ſom amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe iolly felowes whiche had rather haue the name then the thynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Surely &amp; ſo thynke</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I.</speaker>
               <p>Yf he be a kinge whiche by lawe and equyte regardes more the commoditie of his people then his owne lucre / yf he be a biſſhop which alwayes is careful for the lordes flocke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to his paſtorall charge / yf he be a magiſtrate which frankelie and of good wyll dothe make prouyſyon, and dothe all thinge for the comyn welthes ſake / and yf he be a phyloſopher whiche paſſynge not vpon the goodes of this worlde, only geueth hym ſelfe to attayn to a good mynde, and to leade a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous lyfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Lo thus ye may perſey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue what a nombre of ſemblable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples ye may collecte &amp; gether.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a great ſorte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray the tel me wyll you ſaye that all theſe are no men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Nay I feare rather leſt in ſo ſayenge it ſhulde coſt vs our lyues, and
<pb facs="tcp:11687:19"/> ſo myght we our ſelues ſhortelye be no men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Yf man be a reſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, howe ferre dyffers this from all good reaſon, that in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning to the body (for ſo they deſerue rather to be called then goodnes) and in outwarde gyftes whiche dame for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune geues and takes awaye at her ple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſure, we had rather haue the thynge then the name, and in the true and only goodnes of the mynd we paſſe more vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the name then the thynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>So god helpe me it is a corrupte and a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterours iudgement, yf a man marke and conſyder it wel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>The ſelfe ſame reaſon is in contrarie thinges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>I wolde gladly knowe what ye meane by that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>We maye iudge lykewyſe the ſame of the names of thynges to be eſchued, and incommodites which was ſpoken of thynges to be diſſyred and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modites.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe I haue conſidered the thynges well, it apereth to be euen ſo as ye ſaye in dede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>It ſhulde be
<pb facs="tcp:11687:19"/> more feared of a good prynce to be a ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunt in dede then to haue the name of a tyraunt. And yf an euyll byſſhop be a thefe and a robber, then we ſhulde not ſo greatly abhorre and hate the name as the thynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Eyther ſo it is or ſo it ſhuld be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe gather you of the reſt as I haue done of the prynce &amp; the byſſhop.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Me thynkes I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande this gere wonderouſe well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Do not all men hate the name of a fole or to be called a moome, a ſotte, or an aſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Yeas as moche as they do any one thynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>And how ſaye you were not he a ſtarke fole that wold fiſhe with a golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bayte, that wolde preferre or eſteme glaſſe better then precious ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, or whiche loues his horſe or dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges better then his wyfe and his chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>He were as wyſe as waltoms calfe, or madder then iacke of Redyng.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>And be not they as wyſe whiche not aſſygned, choſen, nor yet ones ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by the magiſtrates, but vpon
<pb facs="tcp:11687:20"/> theyr owne heed aduenture to runne to the warres for hoope of a lytle gayne, ieoperdynge theyr bodyes and daunge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge theyr ſoules? Or howe wyſe be they which buſie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe to get, gleyne, and reepe to gyther, goodes and ryches when they haue a mynde deſtitute and lackyng all goodnes? Are not they alſo euen as wyſe that go gorgyouſly appa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rylled, and buyldes goodly ſumptuous houſes, when theyr myndes are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded but neglect fylthye and with all kynde of vyce fowle corrupted? And how wyſe are they whiche are carefull diligent and buſie, about the helthe of theyr body neglectynge and not myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge at all theyr ſoule, in daunger of ſo many deedly ſynnes? And fynally to conclude howe wyſe be they whiche for a lytle ſhorte tranſytorye pleaſure of this lyfe deſerue euerlaſtynge tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and punyſhementes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Euen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſon forſeth me to graunt that they are more then fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyke and folyſhe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Yea
<pb facs="tcp:11687:20"/> but althoughe all the whole worlde be full of ſuche fooles, a man can ſcaſelye fynde one whiche can abyde the name of a foole, and yet they deſerue to be cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led ſo for aſmoche as they hate not the thynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Suerly it is euen ſo as ye ſeye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Ye knowe alſo howe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of a lyar and a thefe are abhorred and hated of all men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>They are ſpyteful and odious names, and abhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of all men, and not withe out good cauſe why.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>I graunte that, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe to commyt adulterie be a more wycked ſynne then thefte yet for al that ſome men reioyſe and ſhewe them ſelfe glad of that name, whiche wolde be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by and by to drawe theyr ſwerdes and fyghte withe a man that wolde or durſt call them theues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>It is true there are many wolde take it euyll as you ſaye in dede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>And nowe it is commyn to that poynt that thoughe there are many vnthryftes and ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d als whiche conſume theyr ſubſtaunce at the
<pb facs="tcp:11687:21"/> wyne and vpon harlottes, and yet ſo wyllynge to continewe openly that all the worlde wonders at them, yet they wyll be offended and take peper in the nooſe yf a man ſhulde call them ruffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans or baudy knaues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Suche fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes thynke they deſerue prayſe for the thynge, and yet for all that they can not abyde the name dewe to the thinge whiche they deſerue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>There is ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlye any name amonges vs more intol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lerable or worſe can be abydden then to he called a lyar or a lyeng fellowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>I haue knowen ſome or this whiche haue kylled men for ſuche a ſpytefull worde as that is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Yea yea but wolde god ſuche haſty fellowes dyd as well abhorre the thinge and hate lienge as well as to be called lyers, was it neuer thy chaunce to be dyſceyued of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man whiche borowinge mony of the appoyntynge the a certayne daye to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paye the ſayd money and ſo performyd not his appoyntment nor kept his day?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:11687:21"/>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Ye as many tymes (god know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) and yet hath he ſworne many a gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous othe and that not one tyme but many tymes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Peraduenture he wolde haue ben ſo honeſt as to haue payed it and yf he had had wherwith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Naye that is not ſo for he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inoughe, but as he thought it better neuer to paye his dettes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>And what call you this in englyſhe, is it not playne lyenge?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Yes as playne as Dunſtable waye, there can not be a lowder lye then this is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Durſte you be ſo bolde to pulle one of theſe good detters of yours by the ſleue and ſaye thus to hym, why haſt thou dyſcey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued me ſo many tymes and broken pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe with me, or to talke to hym in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yne englyſhe, why doeſt thou make me ſo many lyes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Why no ſyr by my trouthe durſt I not, excepte I were myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded before to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge halfe a doſen drye blowes with hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Dothe not ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons, Brekelayers, Carpenters, Smy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes,
<pb facs="tcp:11687:22"/> Goldſmithes, Taylours, diſceyue and diſapoynt vs after the lyke maner daylye promyſynge to do youre worke ſuche a daye and ſuche a daye without any fayle, or further delaye, and yet for all that they parforme not theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe althoughe it ſtande the neuer ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moche vpon hande, or that thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt take neuer ſo moche profyte by it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>This is a wonderous and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge vnſhamefaſt knauerye of all that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I hard of. But and ye ſpeake of bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>akers of promyſe then ye maye reken a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongeſt them lawyers and atturneys at the lawe, which wyl not ſtycke to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe or beare you in hande that they wyll be diligent and erneſt in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſpedie expedicion of your ſute.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Reken ꝙ he, naye ye maye reken ſyxe hundreth mennes names be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyde theſe of ſundrye faculties and occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pacions whiche wyll promyſe more by an ynche of a candle then they wyll per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forme by a whole pounde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Why
<pb facs="tcp:11687:22"/> and ye call this lyenge all the worlde is full of ſuche lyenge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſe alſo lykewyſe that no man can abyde to be called thefe, and yet all men do not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the thynge ſo greatly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>I wolde gladly haue you to declare your mynde in this more playnlye &amp; at large</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>What difference is there betwene hym whiche ſtealeth thy money forthe of thy cofer, and hym whiche forſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and falſely denyeth that whiche thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to his cuſtodie to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued and ſafely kept for thy vſe only, or to ſuche tyme as thou arte mynded to call for it agayne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>There is as they ſay neyther barrell better hearing, but that in my iudgement he is the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer knaue of the twayne whiche robbes a man that puttes his confidence and truſt in hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>yea but howe fewe men are there nowe adayes lyuynge whiche are contente to reſtore agayne that whiche they were put in truſte to kepe, or yf they delyuer it agayne it is
<pb facs="tcp:11687:23"/> ſo dymynyſſhed, gelded, nypped, and pynched, that it is not delyuered whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, but ſome thinge cleues in theyr fyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers, that the prouerbe may haue place where the horſe walloweth there lyeth ſome heares.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>I thynke but a fewe that dothe otherwyſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>And yet for all that there is none of al theſe that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abyde it ones to be called thefe, and yet forſothe they hate not the thing ſo greatly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>That is as trewe as the goſpell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Conſyder me nowe and marke I beſeche the howe the goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of orphanes, pupylls, wardes, and fatherleſſe chyldren be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and vſed, how wylles and teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes be executed and performed, how le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacyes and bequethes be communelye payde, Naye howe moche cleueth and hangeth faſt in the fyngers of the execu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tors or with them that mynyſter and in termedle with the goodes of the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Many tymes they retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and kepe in theyr handes all togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:11687:23"/>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Yea they loue to playe the thefe well inoughe, but they loue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge worſe then to here of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>That is very trewe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Howe lytle dyffers he from a thefe whiche borow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth money of one and other and ſo run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in dette, with this intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe that yf he maye eſcape ſo or fynde ſuche a crafty colour or a ſubtyle ſhyft, he intendeth neuer to paye that he ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Paraduenture he maye be called warer or more craftier the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a thefe is in dede but no poynt better, for it is hard choſyng of a better where there is neuer a good of them bothe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>yea but althoughe there be in euery place a great nombre of ſuch makeſhyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ſlypper marchauntes yet the ſtarkeſt knaue of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all can not abyde to be called thefe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>God onely knoweth euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes hart and mynd, and therfore they are called of vs men that are runne in dette or fer behynde the hande, but not theues for that ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:11687:24"/> vnſwetely and lyke a playne ſong note.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>What ſkyllys it howe they be called amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge men yf they be theues afore god. And where you ſay that god onely knoweth euery mannes hart and mynde, euen ſo euery man knoweth his owne mynde, whether in his wordes &amp; doynges he entende fraude, couyn, dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte, and thefte or no. But what ſay ye by hym whiche when he oweth more then he is worthe, wyll not ſtycke to laſhe prodygallye and ſet the cocke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hoope, and yet yf he haue any money at all lefte to ſpende that awaye vnthryftely, and when he hathe played the parte of a knauyſhe ſpendall in one cytie deludinge and diſceyuyng his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditours, ronnes out of this countre and getteth hym to ſome other good towne, and there ſekynge for ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers and nowe acquayntau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whom he may lykewyſe begyle, yea and playeth many ſuche lyke partes and ſhameful ſhiftes. I praye the tell me dothe not ſuche a
<pb facs="tcp:11687:24"/> greke declare euydentlye by his crafty dealynge and falſe demeanour, what mynde is he of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>yes ſuerly as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uydentlye as can be poſſible. But yet ſuche felowes are wonte to colour and cloke theyr doynges vnder a craftie pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>With what I beſeche the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>They ſaye to owe moche and to dyuers perſones is communely vſed of great men, yea and of kynges alſo as well as of them, and therfore they that intende to be of that diſpoſycyon wyll beare out to the harde hedge the porte of a gentylman and ſoo they wyll be taken and eſtemed for gentilmen of the commune people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>A gentylman and why or to what entent and purpoſe a gentylman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>It is a ſtraunge thynge to be ſpoken howe moche they thynke it is mete for a gentylnan or a horſeman to take vpon hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>By what equytie, authoritie, or lawes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>By none other but by the ſelfe ſame lawes that the Admiralles of the
<pb facs="tcp:11687:25"/> ſees chalenge a proprietie in all ſuche thynges as are caſt vpon the ſhoore by wracke, althoughe the ryghte owner come forthe and chalenge his owne goodes. And alſo by the ſame lawes that ſome other men ſaye all is theyrs whatſoeuer is founde aboute a thefe or a robber whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni</speaker>
               <p>Such lawes as theſe are the arranteſt theues that are myght make themſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>yea and ye may be ſure they wold glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al theyr harts i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their bodies make ſuche lawes yf they coulde mayntayne them or were of power to ſe them execu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, and they myght haue ſome thynge to laye for theyr excuſe if they could pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clayme opyn warre before they fell to robbynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>But who gaue that pryuylege rather to a horſeman then to a foteman, or more to a gentylman the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a good yeman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>The fauoure that is ſhewed to men of warre, for by ſuche ſhyftes and thus they practyſe be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to be good men of warre that they
<pb facs="tcp:11687:25"/> maye be more redy &amp; hanſome to ſpoyle theyr enemyes when they ſhall encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>I thynke Pyrhus dyd ſo exercyſe and breake his yonge ſouldyers to the warres.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>No not Pyrrhus but the Lacedemonians dyd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Mary ſyr hange vp ſuche prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſers or ſoldyers and theyr practiſyng to. But howe come they by the name of horſemen or gentylmen that they vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe ſuche a great prerogatyue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Some of them are gentylme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> borne and it cometh to them by aunceſtrie, ſome bye it by the meanes of mayſtrys mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and other ſome gette it by certayne ſhyftes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>But maye euery man that wyl and lyſt come by it by ſhyftes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Yea why not, euery man maye be a gentylman nowe adayes very well and yf theyr condicions and maners be accordynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>What maners or condicions muſt ſuche one haue I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>Yf he be occupyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute no goodneſſe, yf he can ruffle it
<pb facs="tcp:11687:26"/> and ſwaſhe in his ſatens and his ſilkes and go gorgiouſly apparelled, yf he can ratle in his rynges vpon the fyngers endes, yf he can playe the ruffyan and the horemonger and kepe a gaye hoore gallantlye, yf he be neuer well at eaſe but when he is playenge at the dyſe, yf he be able to matche as moche an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thryfte as hym ſelfe with a newe payre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rdes, yf he ſpende his tyme lyke an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cure vpon bankettinge, ſumptuous fare, and all kynde of pleaſures, yf he talke of no raſcalles nor beggars, but bragge, boſt, face, brace, and crake of caſtelles, towers, and ſkyrmyſſhes, and yf all his talke be of the warres and blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy battels, and playe the parte of crac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge Thraſo throughly, ſuch gaye gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, luſty brutes and ionkers may take vpon them to be at defyaunce withe whome they wyll and lyſt, thoughe the gentylman haue neuer a fote of lande to lyue vpon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boni.</speaker>
               <p>Call ye them horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Mary ſyr ſuche horſemen are wel
<pb facs="tcp:11687:26"/> worthy to ryde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gallowes, theſe are gentylmen of the Iebet of all that euer I haue harde of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <p>But yet there be not afewe ſuche in that parte of Germany called Naſſen or Heſſen.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated by Edmonde Berke And prynted at Cantorbury in ſaynt Paules pariſhe by Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mychell.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
